Last month one of my fans sent me a Penultimate cartridge.
上个月我的一个粉丝给我寄了张Penultimate卡带
This is a modern-day cartridge for the Commodore
VIC-20 and it does a lot of different things.
这是一张当今爱好者自制的VIC-20卡带，拥有许多不同的功能
So in this episode you're going to be seeing
a lot about the VIC-20.
所以在这一集你将看到很多关于VIC-20的东西
And why not?
为什么不呢
This computer holds a special place for me
because it was the first computer I ever owned
这台电脑对于我来说有一些特殊的意义
when I was six years old.
因为它是我在6岁的时候所拥有的第一台电脑
And I think a lot of the time it is completely
overshadowed by the Commodore 64.
但是我觉得很多时候Commodore 64夺走了很多本来它应有的风光
So it doesn't get nearly the attention it
deserves in the world of retro computers.
总之，作为一台古董电脑，它并没有引起人们的注意
There's so much I want to say about this computer,
but I'm going to have to restrain myself because
I’m actually scripting out a full and complete
episode, very detailed, on this computer.
关于这台电脑我有很多想说的，但是因为我在单独准备一期关于它的视频，所以这集我就少说点吧
But, for the time being, suffice it to say,
it was a fairly successful gaming platform
眼下，只要说它是一个有超过300个游戏可用，相当成功的游戏平台就够了
with over 300 games available for it.
That's more games than the ColecoVision, the
Intellivsion, the Atari 5200 or 7800, the
它比 Coleco Vision, Intellivsion, Atari 5200 or 7800, Sega 游戏机 ， TRS-80 彩色电脑
，turbo-graft 16等平台拥有更多的游戏
Sega game gear or the TRS-80 color computer,
or even the turbo-graft 16, and many others.
And from a hardware perspective, as a gaming
machine what was the competition like in 1980?
那么从硬件的角度来看，上世纪80年代的游戏机行业竞争是什么样的呢？
I mean, you had the Apple II and the Atari
400 and 800 machines, The Intellivision, the
市面上有苹果II，Atari 400和800的游戏机，Intellivision, Color Computer，VIC-20和 Atari 2600
TRS-80 Color Computer, the VIC-20 and the
Atari 2600.
That was essentially the gaming market in
1980.
这基本上就是1980年的游戏市场
So, the Apple II was $1,298 just for the machine,
but honestly if you were going to play any
苹果II的售价是1298美元 但老实说，如果你要玩任何游戏，都必须从磁带或者软盘中载入，所以你得花更多的钱
games they'd have to load from tape or more
likely disk, so you'd have to spend even more
money.
And if you wanted a display you'd need to
buy a monitor or buy a separate RF modulator
如果需要显示输出，那你就需要买显示器或买一个单独的射频调制器
for your TV.
So getting into an Apple II was a considerable
expense, and it still had no sound synthesizer
所以，入一个苹果II的费用是相当可观的，而且它还没有用于游戏的声音合成器
for games.
The Atari 400 was a more reasonable proposition
at $440 and could play cartridge games like
Atari 400是一个更合理的选择，售价440美元，可以像真正的游戏机一样玩卡带游戏
a real game machine.
So this would have been serious competition.
所以本应是一场激烈的竞争
The Intellivision was priced competitively
at $299, but it was just a game machine, not
Intellivision的价格是299美元，但它只是一台游戏机，而不是一台电脑
a computer.
The TRS-80 Color computer was barely competitive
at $399, but it had that annoying chicklet
售价为399美元的TRS-80彩色电脑几乎没有什么竞争力，因为它有着讨厌的Chicklet键盘
keyboard and really a lack of any brand-name
commercial game titles since it was only sold
也没有什么大牌的商业游戏 另外还只在Radio Shack销售
in Radio Shack and they didn't allow selling
anything in the store back then with names
还不允许和Atari、Activision或者Parker Brothers的机子放在一家店里销售
like Atari, Activision, or Parker Brothers
on the labels.
The VIC-20 itself sold for $299, and the only
other serious competing game platform of the
VIC-20本身的售价为299美元
day would have been the Atari 2600, which
was sold at a good price, but was alread
而唯一可以竞争的游戏平台是Atari 2600
out of date and the VIC-20 beat it in both
graphics and sound, plus it was a real computer.
但是已经过时了，而VIC-20在图形和声音又是直接秒杀，再加上它又是一台真正的计算机
So, now that I've set the stage of the VIC-20
as a gaming platform, you are about to see
我现在已经说明了VIC-20作为一台游戏机的背景
a LOT of games.
接下来你也即将看到大量的游戏
Because the penultimate cartridge is crammed
full of games.
因为Penultimate卡带就是塞满了游戏
You might be able to compare it to one of
these all-in-one cartridges for the Nintendo.
你也许能把它和任天堂的那种多合一卡带相比较
But the penultimate cartridge is also quite
a bit more than just a games cartridge, which
但是Penultimate卡带不单单只是一张游戏卡带
I’m going to get into after I show you the
games.
别的东西等我展示完游戏再介绍
For the moment, let’s talk about the games!
现在我们还是先来谈谈游戏吧
There’s 40 of them in here!
里面一共有40个游戏
Let me help you visualize what that many VIC-20
cartridges would look like.
让我给你展示一下一般VIC-20卡带的样子
By the way, almost all of the games for the
VIC-20 were, in fact, distributed on cartridge
顺便说一下，事实上几乎所有在VIC-20上运行的游戏都是从卡带上载入的
because it had so very little on board memory.
因为VIC-20它的内存很少
OK, so I'm going to insert this beast into
the computer.
好了，准备插上电脑
By the way, VIC-20 games are notoriously difficult
to insert, but on the bright side they almost
顺便说一句，VIC-20游戏的插入很费劲，但是另一方面，
never have issues with making good contact.
接触就从来不成问题
I've never seen anyone having to blow into
a VIC-20 cartridge!
我从来没见过有人需要往VIC-20的卡带里吹气
I'll also connect a joystick since the vast
majority of these games require one.
这些游戏大部分都需要用到手柄，我也将它连了上去
This is the perfect cartridge to just hook
up your VIC-20 to the living room TV and just
如果你想把的客厅电视和VIC-20连接起来，然后坐下来用手柄操作的话
sit back with a joystick.
那这张卡带非常合适
You don’t need a disk drive or any other
clutter, just like a game console.
你不需要再用一个磁盘驱动器或者其他麻烦的东西 就像一台主机一样就可以了
The first thing you'll see on power up is
a menu.
首先打开来你会看到一个菜单
You can use your joystick to scroll through
the list of games.
你可以用你的手柄滚动游戏菜单
You can also use the cursor keys to jump entire
screens and then type the number of the game
也可以使用键盘实现屏幕光标的跳转，然后输入你想要的游戏的编号
you want.
Ok, so I’m just going to take these one
by one in the order they appear, starting
好吧，那我就拿这些按他们出现的顺序，逐一开始玩
with Aggressor.
第一个是Aggressor
Now, I’ll be honest, I’ve never seen this
game before.
老实说，之前我从没见过这个游戏
It appears to be some sort of Defender clone.
看起来像是克隆版的Defender
And I guess visually, it looks okay.
看起来我觉得看起来不错
I looked it up and saw that this was an early
game by Jeff Minter, or Jeff Minter, I’m
我查了一下，是Jeff Minter早期的一个游戏
not sure how to pronounce that, who later
also founded Llamasoft.
并不清楚如何发音 他之后还创办了Llamasoft
The next game is Amazing Maze, and unfortunately
this game doesn’t really get my blood pumping
下一个游戏是Amazing Maze，不幸的是这个游戏也没有让我感到热血澎湃
either.
I’m honestly surprised it was included.
我甚至于很惊讶它被包括在内
Next up is Avenger.
再下一个游戏是Avenger（复仇者)
Ok, if it isn’t obvious, this is definitely
a space-invaders clone.
好吧，这肯定是我以前从没见过的太空入侵者克隆游戏
And I’ve actually never seen it before until
now.
Normally, I am not a big fan of clone games,
but in the case where the original game is
通常来说，虽然我并不喜欢山寨游戏，但是在这个游戏根本没有在这个平台上发布的情况下
not available on a platform, a good clone
is okay in my opinion.
我觉得好的山寨也是可以接受的
And this is exactly the case here, as space
invaders was not available on the VIC-20 or
这就是这里的情况，并不存在VIC-20或C64版的太空入侵者
C64.
This clone is actually really well made, right
down to the bases, the aliens, and the little
这个克隆游戏真的很好，完全还原了基地，外星人，还有能看见的偶尔碰到的小飞碟在空中飞过
flying saucer that sometimes comes across
the top.
So, definitely a great game to be included
here.
因此，这绝对是一个被包括在内的好游戏了
Next up is Battlezone, which everyone is already
probably familiar with.
接下来是战争地带，或许每个人都已经对此很熟悉
This is one of the first first-person shooter
type games.
这是第一批第一人称射击游戏之一
This version is a bit blocky on the graphics,
but seems playable enough, however I must
这个游戏版本图形感觉分辨率低了点 但是也可以玩了
admit I’ve never really been fond of this
game.
但我必须承认我从来没有真正喜欢过这个游戏
Here’s centipede.
再是centipede
This is another official Atari licensed version.
这是另一个Atari官方授权的版本
And it seems fairly true to the original arcade,
I have no complaints about this game!
这像是真实的原始接机游戏，我对这个游戏没有什么不满意的地方
Next up is Choplifter.
接下来是Choplifter
I actually used to play the C64 version of
this game as a kid.
我小时候其实还玩过这个游戏的C64版本
It turns out the VIC-20 version is almost
identical in game play, with just slightly
结果是 VIC-20的版本在游戏体验上基本上和C64的是一致的
chunkier graphics.
只是图形方面分辨率稍微低了点
I accidentally hit one of the function keys
when I started playing that changed the foreground
另外我在玩的时候不小心碰到了一个功能键
color.
发现可以更改游戏的背景颜色
So let me pick a different color.
来选个不同的颜色
Believe It or not, that is a common feature
on a lot of old VIC-20 games, that you can
而且其实很多老的VIC-20游戏都支持修改背景颜色
change the foreground color since many of
the games operate essentially as monochrome
因为很多这些游戏本质上也就是一个黑白游戏
games with some different colored background
areas.
然后加上点不同颜色的背景区域
So I’m going to rescue my guys here and
try to get away before that tank shoots me!
所以我要在坦克射击我之前营救出同伴并离开这里
OK, so this is defender.
Defender就是这样了
I showed a clone of this a few minutes ago
called Aggressor, but this is the officially
几分钟之前我才展示过一个叫Aggressor的clone
licensed version here.
但是这个是官方授权的版本
I’m not sure which is best.
我也不确定哪个比较好
I also find it ironic that one is called defender
and the other is called aggressor.
而且有趣的是一个叫Defender（防御者）另外一个叫Aggressor（入侵者）
Anyway, not much to really talk about on this
one, so on to the next.
无论如何，没什么太多可讲的，下一个
This is Demon Attack.
这个是Demon Attack
I’ve never played this game until today.
我之前从来没玩过这个游戏
And it seems pretty obvious how to play it,
it’s sort of like space invaders or Galaga
玩法还是相当清晰明了的 就有点像Space Invaders或者Galaga
maybe.
But for some reason it isn’t really gripping
me much, so I’m going to move on to the
但出于某些原因，我并没有什么大兴趣
next.
Next up is Dig Dig, and it should need no
explanation.
下一个是Dig dig，这个应该不需要过多解释了
The gameplay here is pretty true the arcade.
游戏体验和真的接机差不多的
As expected with this machine, the graphics
are a bit chunky, but that doesn’t make
正如和对机能的预计一样 图形效果就差了点
it any less enjoyable to play!
不过毫不影响游戏性
Next up is Donkey Kong.
下一个是Donkey Kong
So, this is an officially licensed Nintendo
game for the VIC-20.
这个是任天堂官方授权的VIC-20版本
Most of the games I’ve shown so far have
been Atari games.
到目前为止我展示过的大部分游戏都是Atari游戏
So you get to see the character of Mario and
Princess Peach here, although I don’t think
可以看见马里奥和Peach公主
they had been officially named at this point
in history.
虽然我觉得这个时候他们应该还没有被正式命名
I don’t have a top 10 games list for the
VIC-20, but I probably should make one.
我还没有排过VIC-20的Top10游戏列表，或许我应该列一个
But if I did, this game would definitely be
on the list.
如果真做的话 那这个肯定是上榜游戏
I think it’s one of the most well-made games
for the system.
我觉得这应该是这个平台上制作最精良的游戏之一
I would also like to point out some of the
challenge in producing a game like this on
另外考虑到这个系统没有硬件精灵 单元颜色也受限
a system that has no sprites and colors confined
to little cells on the screen.
Most of these games are really impressive
from a programming standpoint.
这些游戏从编程角度来说都算是非常惊人了
So this is the official port of Frogger from
Parker Brothers.
这个是来自Parker Brothers的Frogger的官方移植
While this game is playable enough, it is
clear the programmers on this one were a bit
虽然可玩度也不错 但是显然这里的程序员有点点偷懒
lazy or perhaps less creative than some of
these other games I’ve shown, as you can
或者说创意不足
see black squares around everything, a sure
sign they are just moving characters around
可以看见东西附近的黑色方块 说明他们只是在屏幕上移动字符
on the screen in a grid rather than trying
to move anything pixel by pixel.
而不是一个像素一个像素的复制
And here’s the official port of Galaxian
from Atari and you can clearly see the objects
这个是Atari官方移植的Galaxian
move much smoother, pixel by pixel.
显然里面的东西是逐像素点移动的了
So again, some great work went into this.
这张卡带里确实还是有不少良作的
And this is a great port of the game, in my
opinion.
在我看来，这个移植也非常不错
You can even hear they made good use of all
of the voices on the sound chip too.
甚至可以听到他们也是充分利用了音源芯片的各个声部
Next up is Gorf, and this is an officially
licensed port.
下一个是Gorf，也是官方授权移植
And it’s pretty decent except for the movement
of the aliens.
除了外星人的移动外，相当不错
Next game is Jelly Monsters.
下一个游戏是Jelly Monsters（水果怪物）
I’ve never actually played or even heard
of this game.
我也是之前从来没有听说过这个游戏
Apparently it can be played with the keyboard
or joystick.
键盘或者摇杆都可以操作
This is obviously a Pacman clone.
显然是个山寨版的Pacman（吃豆人）
And you know, it’s not bad really.
The movement on this game is so fluid I could
almost forget the machine has no sprites,
except when you see two objects of different
colors get close you can see the color-cell
clash.
But I can’t fault the programmers, as that’s
a hardware limitation.
Next on the list is Jungle Hunt.
I am not going to lie, I’ve never been a
fan of this game on any platform.
And so it’s hard to really judge it here
because I hate the game one way or another.
Sorry, I’m biased but at least I admit it.
And here’s Jupiter Lander.
Admittedly, I’ve never played this and I
can’t quite figure it out.
I thought it would be similar to lunar lander
but the controls don’t seem to make any
sense.
Besides, how would you land on Jupiter in
the first place since it is a gas giant?
OK, so here we have Lode Runner, I think the
first Broderbund game I’ve seen on here.
I’m not a huge fan of this game, but I see
a lot of love for this game over on the Apple
II Facebook page, so I’m curious what they
think of this port.
I mean, it seems decently well made.
Next up is Lunar Leeper, by Sierra Online
in 1981.
Admittedly, I didn’t know Sierra ever made
any VIC-20 games, I guess I was wrong.
Anyway, I’ve never played this game before
either.
And at fist I wasn’t even sure which creature
I was supposed to be playing.
I saw the little leaping critters so I thought
with a name like Lunar Leeper, that I’d
be playing the leeper.
But, apparently I move the flying saucer.
The animation is really smooth and I think
one of the reasons they were able to do that
is they are just treating the play area like
a monochrome bit-mapped screen.
However, I can’t quite figure out how to
play this, so I’m going to move on.
OK, so now we have Monster Maze.
It’s a first person maze program, it’s
a little hard to navigate as I seem to run
into walls faster than I expect.
And the whole game clearly runs in text mode,
just using various line characters.
But, it actually looks pretty decent, despite
that.
Still, I couldn’t quite master the game
play, I think I’d need to read the manual.
Next up is Moon Patrol.
This game looks better than the Atari 2600
version, but that’s about it.
The animation is pretty smooth, which again
on the VIC-20 is always a challenge due to
lack of sprites.
It is one of the few VIC-20 games with a sound
track, although the music is just on one voice
and the sound effects are on the other voices.
So, while I am not a big fan of the official
Pac-Man port, I think they did a much better
job with Ms. Pac-Man.
The game looks kind of blocky compared to
other systems, due to the low resolution on
this system, but otherwise this game plays
really well and I would definitely include
it in my top 10 games list for the VIC-20.
This is another Jeff Minter game called Attack
of the Mutant Camels.
So at this point we’re already seeing his
love for Camels and Llamas.
I don’t know if I’m playing grid runner
of centipede.
I don’t see anything that actually looks
like a camel, but that’s probably due to
the low resolution.
Next up is Omega Race.
This game is sort of special to me because
it’s the first cartridge game I ever owned
for the VIC-20 back in 1982.
I’ve only ever seen this game on the VIC-20
and Commodore 64, but apparently it was first
an arcade and was also available on the Atari
2600 and the Coleco.
I always felt the game was sort of like playing
asteroids, but a little more involved.
And one of the things I learned early on was
that it was best to move only in one dimension
and try to shoot the aliens..
The moment I started moving the ship in a
second dimension, I’d always crash into
something.
This game is essentially monochrome, other
than the title screen.
It’s possible the original arcade may have
been a vector based CRT like asteroids, which
would explain the monochrome choice.
Anyway, I spent many hours of my childhood
playing this.
OK, so next on the list is the official Pac
Man port from Atari.
To be honest, it isn’t all that great, although
I guess it’s definitely better than the
Atari 2600 version.
So, moving on.
Let’s have a look at Pharaohs Curse.
This is another one I’ve never heard of
until now.
The game reminds me of Montezuma’s Revenge.
And it’s definitely a game that would require
some practice to ever get very far, but it
looks like it could be fun.
On to the next.
So this is the official Pole Position from
Namco.
There’s not really a lot for me to say here.
I mean, the game looks and plays fine considering
the limitations of the system.
But for some reason, I just don’t find it
to be any fun.
And..
Here’s the official port of Q*Bert for the
VIC-20.
Unfortunately, I have nothing good at all
to say about this port.
Not only does Q*Bert not move..
I mean he just sort of appears on the next
cube almost like he teleports around instead
of jumps.
But there are black squares around the characters.
This is because the game essentially runs
in text-mode and they’ve just re-defined
some of the characters.
I think this may actually be the worst port
of Q*Bert on any system.
Now, don’t get me wrong.
I understand the limitations of this machine
and there’s a lot of problems to overcome
not having any sprites, especially with the
diagonal lines crossing through color cell
areas.
But, even if they had to make the game monochrome,
I would have preferred some animation over
the extra color.
Anyway, rant over, onto the next.
This is Radar Rat Race, which is unique to
the VIC-20 and the Commodore 64.
The game is obviously a rip off of Rally X,
but I always sort of liked the little rats
chasing after the cheese and avoiding the
cats.
The game is ridiculously simple from a technical
level, and this would be super easy to code.
But oddly enough, this was a decently fun
game from my childhood.
Next up is Robotron 2084.
I never actually cared much for this game,
I think I preferred Berzerk, which had a similar
type of gameplay.
This is Shamus, a game I’ve never heard
of.
I kept waiting to see Alfred Hitchcock walk
across the screen or something.
Anyway, This seems to be another sort of Berzerk
or Robotron type game, although the graphics
are a little more interesting in this one.
Next up is Star Battle, another one I have
never played before.
It is most definitely a Galaxian clone, although
I definitely prefer the official Galaxian
port over this one.
I tried playing Submarine Commander, but I
honestly couldn’t figure out how it works
so I’d need to find the manual and read
it, I suppose.
Super Slots is pretty much what it sounds
like.
And there’s not a lot I can say about it,
other than it’s a lot machine.
Next up is Threshold, and it’s another Sierra
Online game made back in 1981.
I’ve never played this before, but I still
get the sense this is another Galaxian or
space invaders clone and it’s just not gripping
me.
Next up is Tutankham.
I hope I’m saying that correctly.
Never played this one.
The game looks kind of interesting, but I
definitely need some practice to get very
far with this.
So the last 4 games on this cartridge are
all Scott Adams adventure games.
These were quite popular back in the 80s on
a variety of computer platforms.
These are just text games, and so the gameplay
is going to be pretty similar regardless of
which computer platform you play them on,
so there’s not a lot really to show here.
OK, so now that I’ve covered the games..
and by the way, there’s a lot more games
for the VIC-20 than what was on the cartridge,
but I do think that most of the best games
for the platform were on here.
But what else does the cartridge do?
Well, for one thing it adds more memory.
So, you know the original VIC-20 only had
5K of RAM, only 3 and a half available to
the user.
Commodore officially sold 3K, 8K, and 16K
RAM upgrade cartridges and they also had the
super expander which was 3K with an enhanced
BASIC to go along with it.
I did a whole episode on that one, but anyway,
the penultimate cartridge can upgrade the
VIC-20 all the way to 35K.
Plus it has a menu driven system do allow
you to pick a variety of memory banking configurations,
that some software would require.
So, I’ve shown you a bunch of older games,
but what about newer games?
Yes, people are actually still writing new
games for the old VIC-20.
Myself, included.
Back in 2009, I actually wrote as an experiment
game called Planet-X1, Ironically, I’ve
never actually seen the game work on a real
VIC-20 because I wrote it on an emulator and
the game requires 32K of RAM, which I didn’t
have a 32K Ram expansion card before.
Well, now I can, so now I’m going to play
the game on a real VIC-20 and see if it works.
So, how do I get the game over, well I have
one of these SD-2-IEC adapters, which works
on any Commodore machine, including the VIC-20.
Oh, and guess what, the penultimate cartridge
actually supports this device directly, as
you can see right here on the menu.
So, let’s give it a try.
So this is a directory of what’s on my SD
card.
Most of these are C64 games.
Anyway, here’s planet X1.
So you can see I wrote this in 2009, and that’s
my old yahoo email, I don’t even use that
address anymore.
By the way, this is actually just text characters,
I wanted this game to all fit in RAM and there
wasn’t enough room for a lot of fancy bit-mapped
screens.
So even the main menu here is just colorful
text characters.
So I’m going to have it generate a random
map, this actually takes a little while.
This is likely the only real-time strategy
game ever made for the VIC-20.
Somebody sent me a screen capture from their
cell phone, by the way, where apparently this
game was shown on screen of the TV show halt
and catch fire sometime in season 2.
But I haven’t watched the whole season yet
so I haven’t figured out which episode it
was from.
Anyway, it looks like one of the enemy bases
ended up right next to me, so I’m going
to blow his base to kingdom come before he
has a chance to build anything.
So now you can see the enemy number has reduced
to two.
So I’ll need to scout around the map and
find the other two.
And wouldn’t you know it, I ran my tank
right off into the lava.
I still have one tank left so I’ll switch
to that one, and go see what I can find.
Now, while I’m searching for the other bases,
they will start generating enemy fighters
which will come looking for my base, so time
is sort of the essence here.
The map is really big and so it could take
a while.
And well, crap, I just lost my second tank.
The game is eventually over, even though I
never really added any code to end the game.
So, I never actually finished coding Planet
X1.
It was really going to do a lot more things
than it ended up doing.
It was more of an experiment really, and at
the time I made it back in 2009 there seemed
to be zero interest in the game.
So I just kind of finished it up to the point
I was satisfied that it completed my experiment.
But, for those that are interested, it is
available free for download on my website.
I was also sent this game on cassette tape
to review.
It’s called Pentagorat and it’s distributed
on cassette tape.
But notice it says is requires a VIC-20 +
32K of RAM.
I know that’s a little hard to see.
Anyway, so I should be able to use it with
the penultimate cartridge.
So heck, I’ll just give it the maximum 35K
and see how it works.
OK, so they’ve given us a little fast loader
system with a countdown, which is nice because
most games just sit there saying loading and
you don’t know if it is even working or
not.
Oh wow..
This is definitely the nicest loader screen
I’ve ever seen on a VIC-20 game.
It’s actually amazing that they can do all
this while still loading the game too.
OK, well, I’m not going to make you sit
here for the entire thing.. let’s skip ahead!
OK, so this is interesting.
The first thing I notice is that they are
using 40-columns text, which has to be generated
on a bit-mapped screen because the VIC-20
hardware only does 22 columns.
And it’s surprisingly readable.
Keep in mind this is coming from a real VIC-20
computer, not an emulator.
Even these sound effects are impressive because
while the VIC-20 does have 4 voices, they
can only do noise or square wave with no ADSR
envelope.
So they are really manipulating some registers
to get these effects!
OK, so this is the game.
It appears I’m some sort of 3D jelly creature
or something and I’m trapped in a room.
The graphics are very impressive, even though
they are monochrome.
OK, so the door is locked.
So, I guess I have to figure out how to get
out of this room.
OK, I eventually determined that jumping on
this grating will get me out.
OK, so are these killer smiley faces?
I don’t know, either way the animation is
impressive.
Well, whatever I did, I died.
Well, this is certainly a game I will need
to spend some more time playing.
It’s actually really impressive for the
hardware it’s running on.
So, for those that are interested, I did put
a link down in the description field for where
you might be able to go purchase a copy of
Pentagorat.
I think you can download it for free if you
want to use it in an emulator.
So anyway, that about wraps it up for this
episode.
So, stick around for the next one!