好的让我们开始吧
接下来的演讲是关于MOS 6502 CPU的逆向工程的
就是Apple II, NES和C64上使用的CPU
有请演讲嘉宾Michael Steil
谢谢（啪啪啪啪啪啪）
大家好
正如大家刚才所闻，本讲的主题是MOS 6502 CPU的逆向工程
我的名字是Michael Steil(用德语和英语各念了一遍)
副标题是 60分钟里的3510个晶体管
让我先来了解下观众的情况吧
之前写过汇编的观众让我看见你们的双手~
（2333333）呜哦好好好那谁没写过...不知道汇编是什么
很好 那有谁之前写过6502的汇编么
好的……开头十分钟你们这群写过6502汇编的人不要觉得无聊啊~
那你们有谁玩过6502模拟器或者是在FPGA上实现过6502？
一个两个三个四个……？好吧
那有谁是6502的原始设计组成员吗
（2333333）（啪啪啪啪啪）
看来大家都很诚实……
接下来给不熟悉6502历史的观众一个简介
6502的出品公司，MOS，是一群从摩托罗拉辞职的人在1974年创办的。
他们之前是就在摩托罗拉的6800 CPU小组
这个小组的核心成员是Chuck Peddle
他带领这个团队在1975年推出了6502
这个芯片被用在了很多当时的电脑上
比如这边的乔布斯和沃兹两位
所以说6502是个很受欢迎的CPU
被用在了以下所有设备中：
Apple I, Apple II,  BBC Micro, 全系列的Commodore
Atari全系8位机 //Gaming console 和 System？
任天堂的NES和SNES，以及……
Bender和Flexo！（《飞出个未来》中的角色）
还有不要忘了T-800系列终结者……
other cpus which were kind of successful
like the z80 but if you compare them
672 had sixty percent few transistors is
what's much more optimized it wasn't as
powerful but it was even faster
it was more constrained but it was also
more elegant and some people would say
that elegance or perfection comes from
simplicity anyway so my talk consists of
three parts part number 16 / - from top
down meaning programming model how you
would interact with it so don't feel
bored second 165 or two from the bottom
up
meaning how to disassemble a 65 / - how
to look at the gates how to take
photographs how to understand what's
going on inside at the gate level and
then in the third third pieces from the
inside out
meaning what have we learned from
deconstructing the 65 / - what do we
know about the components how do they
interact
where do all these weird quirks and
stuff come from
so part number 16 of our two from top
down whenever you want to start with a
new cpu you would start with some data
sheet or something
let's not do that let's just look at
code for all those who haven't seen a
65-64 code
let's walk through some structions here
and sta store accumulator you have three
registers a XY jsr jump subroutine this
is the call instruction led a load
accumulator compared to that compares
the a register DC branch if Carrie clear
so it branches if it's lower than the
compared value jump the serpentine again
then there's the addition instruction
you always have to clear the carry flag
before you add because the Kerry also
gets added if you don't want the extra
carry be Q branch equal so it's also
always interested in these
in this very low level kind of
programming is to know how the encoding
works
so the opcodes here the opcode is always
eight bits in size so it was a 1 by top
code and which encodes both the
instruction and the addressing mode and
the operand is either zero one or two
bites
so at CLC clear Carrie doesn't have an
operand so it's a single byte
instruction and goes up to three bites
for the jump subroutine which has a
16-bit address after it you can see an
interesting thing here in the first line
already store and got a 56
it's not something in memory memory is
16 bits is 16 bits wide 16 bits
addresses but in this case because in
the first page of memory
there's an extra encoding which makes
the instruction shorter and even faster
so from a more theoretical point of view
what's the programming model and you
have the a register the accumulator it
stores everything and it transfers
everything whenever you handle data when
ever do to you do arithmetic and logic
it goes through your single a register
and the index registers which aren't as
powerful they can count up and down and
produced as an index in in accessing an
array but you can't do any of the
arithmetic logic on them
you have the process status register
it's a bit
you have four bits in there which are
about arithmetic and logic one bit
which signals its decimal mode i'll talk
about this mode later
it's quite boring and there's two more
bits about exceptions for attending the
program counter at sixteen 16-bit
address spaces so it's a 16-bit program
counter and the stack pointer is also 16
bits and management has to be an address
but the upper eight bits are fixed
they're always hot color to one so the
second register is actually only eight
bits
so this has some applications to the
whole programming model hear about the
address space 64 kilobytes of address
space and the first two pages of 256
bytes each our special so first page for
the zeroth pages 0 page goes up to FF
and it's meant for all these addressing
modes where if your address is it falls
within the first page of memory then you
have a special encoding
and everything is faster and there are
some things you can only do with zero
page because the the system is rather a
registered constraint you only have this
accumulator register 10 pages very
useful and the stack is always
constrained to the first page
szostak counts down from 01 FF down to 0
1 0 0 so this rather complicated slide
and it'll get worse supposed to give you
an overview of all the instructions that
exist and how to put them into into some
or somewhere and so that you have seen
all the members at some point so you
don't have to
in case you don't know this already you
don't have to remember these things
this load instructions you can load from
memory into the accumulator into x and y
if you want to store
asdasdasd y into memory you can transfer
between registers that two groups of
read modify write instructions
the shift instructions work with the
accumulator or with memory you can
decrement an increment memory and as
well as the index registers because
index you have to count up you have to
come down and also done by the ALU is
addition and subtraction as well as the
boolean operations and there's the the
other two which this video we compare
one is basically just a subtraction but
only stores the flags and not the result
and the bit is an end only stores there
were the flags of the results
speaking about flags you can set and
clear some flags and you can branch
depending on whether flag is set or
cleared so these are the four arithmetic
and logic bits in the program of
processor status register
there's also the the unconditional jump
and jump subroutine and RTS is a
function call and function return and if
you want to do software interrupts and
interrupt work the same way but there's
a soft interrupt break and return from
interrupt which just the reverse and for
stack
you can only push the a register as well
as the stack as well as the their
process of status register and these are
all the instructions that exists
so for all the general-purpose
instructions these are the addressing
modes that can be used in combination
with these there's an immediate
addressing mode for using constants
absolute addressing modes absolute and x
and y indexed the same always with zero
patience to special ones for special 0
page stuff which work around some other
deficiencies of the design or some
limitations of the design
let's walk through the more important
addressing modes for now so immediate
addressing you have the hash sign right
there
you load a constant in the accumulator
in this case lda load a so if we do that
we have the constant of 17 in a absolute
addressing means you have a 16-bit our
print their fuel load from 314 we look
up in memory address 314
what we get is a 31 and we have 34 1 in
a and then 0 page addressing is this
optimization we
it's a different encoding we only have
an 8-bit operant we load from a dress to
look it up in your page and we find a0
a0 absolute , X means absolute plus X so
the X register
it's added to the constant pointer that
we encode in the instruction stream so a
200 plus X if X is a in our example we
love from address
- Oh a look it up to a that's 52
so we assume that a 200 we just have an
array of bytes and x is iterating over
those absolute , why
same thing with why register that pretty
symmetric the same exist with zero page
but the interesting thing is he here
that there's always there's a wrap
around inside 0 page so if X in this
case is 16 or above it would wrap around
20 again so you cannot exit 0 page with
this indexing
same with 0 pitch , X comma Y now there
are two more and more interesting once
the indirect ones because as I said we
register start we don't even have a
16-bit registers at all so what if you
want to use a . if you have a 16-bit .
you cannot hold it in a register
I like on the ca for example so you have
to store these pointers in 0 page and
you can use 0 page as pointers and then
use them directly instructions like this
one listens in this addressing 10 page x
indexed indirect means that we assume
that ad in the paper in this example we
have an array of pointers and windex the
array with X and would then we load from
one of these pointers
so what the CPU does it looks at a c HC
because exorcizo it indexes that it gets
the pointer little indian the correct
indigenous as everyone knows and it
loads from that address c43 yet there's
another look up
gets the value into a so it's double
indirect it's slow takes five cycles or
six cycles or something then the same
thing we're not the same thing this is 0
page first indirect and then X Y index
which is much more useful because the
streets
14 and 15 in 0 page is a point as a
16-bit pointer this point in this case
at fourteen fifteen is da 200 and then
afterwards we add Y of 28 so we read
from d 8 28 so only whenever you have to
count up somewhere and you don't know
the point to put in 0 page and you can
work with that . from their stack
doesn't have much addressing it's all
implicit instructions stack works like
this normally you would initially lies
it to a fifth which is the top of step
if you put something on the stack it
stores at first and then decrement the
stack pointer
let's do that again let's push something
it stores it with a stack pointer points
and decrements stack pointer
so if we pull something then it
increments the stack pointer and then
read from the address
let's do it again increment and read
so this decimal is something that I
guess what you must be a seventies guy
in a tease guy to fully understand
decimal mode or maybe maybe people that
financial stuff on the Commodores and
Ataris so decimal obesity binary coded
decimal is meant to to optimize the way
you store numbers integer numbers which
would print anyway so in a normal case
if you add two to nine you would get be
X additional be but if you have a
decimal mode turned on then
without this be any slower anything you
will get a result of 11 which is hex 11
which is
I mean wrong in the binary sense but
from our decimal perspective this would
be the correct answer
so this was all the user mode kind of do
so far as more systems perspective these
vectors are interesting what happens
with interrupts with reset and i RQ
there are three vectors at the top of
the address space for any my own mask
will interrupt for the recent vector and
for the IQ vector at the very top of
memory will talk about these vectors
later that's interesting thing
so looking at the all the instructions
that we have been looking at all the
addressing modes that we have if we
combine them if this if you were
completely completely orthogonal being
able to combine every general purpose
operation with every addressing mode it
wouldn't fit into the 256 different op
codes
so what they did with the opcodes is
only include the ones would really make
sense the ones which are most
interesting most important so only about
sixty percent of the opcode space is
used and the rest is just well they say
it's undefined
so let's walk real quick through another
example here this is something taken
from some random room somewhere
you might have seen the code might have
used the code we learned something from
zero page we compare it against a
constant if it's not that constant let's
jump out
let's get the the hybrid the upper 8-bit
let's also compare it to a constant it's
not 65 or two so let's jump out
otherwise we did a subtract there so we
have a zero in a now so we store 0 into
we copy the 0 into the why register we
load an 80 and put it into twelve eleven
twelve we now have a point of the ex
8,000 we load an index register of a of
a which is 10 so we countdown 10 from
somewhere we use that industry is just
the right there we load something from
wrong
so we index summer Rae counting down
from ten mask of some bits story at that
pointer at a thousand plus y increment Y
if there's no overflow skip the next
instruction otherwise increment that 80
that is stored there to anyone
and so on and then count down the X so
the 10 down to zero also loop recommend
how many times you want to do it that's
another parameter that we got a branch
and RTS returned from the protein so you
can see the parameters that we got were
stored in 11 12 and 0 page and 40 60
page so every time we have to do a lot
about the zero page
now the question is what does this code
do so if you have ever used one of the
later pet models the , pits
if you said this on the command line and
wait instruction is a legitimate
instruction does interesting stuff
if it if you use the concept of 65 / -
it would do that
now why is that that's because well Bill
Gates wrote it , door
I'm licensed like Microsoft basic for
the pet then went back to Microsoft for
a bug-fix release for later versions of
the pet and Microsoft kind of got pissed
because they didn't they didn't include
them and then Microsoft anyway it's a
common basic so that just put this
easter egg in and it's a pretty it's
proved we were pretty sure that it's
really Bill Gates who wrote it because
back at those times 76 77
microsoft hit three employees and one of
them could encode and the other one is
EAD and
so he Bill Gates did rights to vote to
hold at some point
what's interesting about an architecture
like that and architectures that you
know the length of your cycle is also
about understanding what's actually
going on inside not just about
optimization so every memory access is a
single cycle the whole system is very
memory bound so mostly only look at how
many memory access do you have for
executing instructions and you know how
many cycles it will take but there's a
special case of every instruction at
least takes two cycles
if we go through this real quick a lot
of 10 page takes three cycles because
you have the load you have the operation
then you have to load from zero page to
compare has to because the instruction
is two cycles it doesn't do any other
fetch and this one has to because it's
also provide instruction if the branch
is taken as an extra and an extra cycle
there
we have we've had this one this one that
the this transfer is only a single bite
but we have a minimum of two cycles then
this one is interesting
the load the operand one operand -
that's three fetchers already then the
actual fetched from memory
so that's four but in case we have an
overflow in case we have a carry into
into the eea here the be one page in
here then the air
Lu has to do one extra step so that's
five instructions and let's go through
all these real quick so six for
something more complicated an increment
of zero pages 5 and what can really kill
performances and RTS or jump subroutine
an RTS in a combination are already 12
cycles that you're wasting right there
so think of it as specific some weird
things about it
some you could consider bugs some just
well you don't care but why do they
happen
so for example if you increment
something in memory what you would
expect us
you read it you write it but what
happens is it reads it
it writes back the original value
sometimes within those four cycles or
six cycles and then it stores the new
value so from a software perspective you
cannot see the difference but from a
hardware perspective you can measure
that and you can build a computer around
that and you can make use of that oddity
and build your copy protections or
application around things like this
this one is a real bug if you have a
break instruction
I mean you wouldn't have it in real code
but in a debugger if you normally use it
for debugging and you put your break in
if you want to know where your cold wind
but if you have a break and real code
and an interrupt happens at the same
time then your break we'll just get lost
the break will not be done just
interrupt will be handled and the this
one big question mark here about illegal
opcodes this is this is the one thing
that so many people have looked into
what
what happens if we use all these up all
the other options what if we just put a
2 into the instruction stream what
happens to this computer doesn't crash
does it do nothing
does it do something useful useless the
answer is all of the above depending on
what should you use many people have
done a lot of research on that and
compiled these tables if you use that
code most of them don't really make all
that much sense it's mostly a
combination of other things
some do make sense so now the question
is how can we find out what exactly is
going on without just describing what we
measured so we have to go from bottom up
we have to understand from a transistor
level
what's going on inside the CPU so part
two from bottom up
so if we want to
dive into the inner workings of a
superior we could look at data sheets
but yeah we get something like pinouts
we can also get something like timing
diagram state
tell us something about what's going on
so the original documentation back in
those days world wasn't that bad
you can also get a schematic diagrams
are block diagrams like this one but
this particular one is as neither useful
nor correct because for example this one
internal bus but there's no internal but
there's actually two into our buses and
that's a very in a very important
difference what we can find some other
timing diagrams for example if you have
an absolute index instruction
what happens in every single cycle
that's useful but still doesn't really
tell us what's going on especially with
the legal up cars or anything like that
so what can we do we can we get the
extra information we could like dive
down from up and just ask someone asked
that company
maybe you have some more documentation
what
well we cannot really ask them because
they got bought by Commodore 1976 must
doesn't exist or hasn't existed for a
very long time with interesting , never
change the markings on the chip until
all at least until nineteen ninety or so
until they would finally switch the
camera semiconductor group CSG and so
most of my strips you can you will find
will actually say moss still
but , for themselves got bankrupt in
then ask about them Jim to micro
electronics cattle and some of the fabs
has come with a retailer German retailer
which also get bankrupt in 95 and this
court was supposed to buy some stuff
gateway bought all the amiga IP and all
the Commodore IP contact but other all
the other
all the retail business with and spun
off a company and they renamed
themselves so their commentary is out
there somewhere and someone is working
on the Amigo as the source code of that
is already there but who would you
really ask about who would you contact
about getting more information about
that
well you could contact the original
designers you could do that but the
problem there is we can't really ask
them so do you maybe have another DVD
floppy disk type a paper tape punch card
or something
they didn't have any of that because 6 f
of 2 and other supplies from that time
were designed completely by hand
there were no computers involved so what
you can see here is to lay out engineers
cutting rubylee that some kind of
plastic foil cutting the the actual mask
that was later used that was later
shrunk to about a square millimeter and
reduced to two are burned those
processors so it
people wouldn't probably have some
copies of these big sheets but some of
these that this documentation some of
the stuff might still exist so in 95
something showed up
there's a somewhat wrote a paper about
something and it had this nice
she to sit it's some original schematic
diagram from the 65 / - it doesn't say
how he got it but it looks really good
it's rather i love really nicely reverse
engineered or it's an original if we
have a quick look at it we can see
there's a lot of program counter logic
it's rather details so you can see a lot
of what's going on it and not all of it
makes sense so by just looking at this
you wouldn't really know what's going on
yet but that means that it probably is
done by someone who knew a lot about it
so the cycle counting goes on here the
code is stored in the instruction
register and then forwarded to the
decode rom and we have the registers
here they are the two buses the d-bus
and the s bus which connect the
different registers to the ALU
and this is the ALU but also surface
just recently is a couple of pages and
it seems to be the the complete
schematic diagram of a 65 / - but it
doesn't seem to be the original it's in
his markings about Atari 1985
I think 94 and it's just really engineer
or something or some someone copied by
hand and it's it's missing a lot of the
original meaning and interesting
markings there
there's another one a couple of pages
this one is not complete rockwell 1982
handwritten
this looks more like the original
because there's also the corrections and
everything and it's a lot more useful
but yeah it's all not complete but the
question is where would you look if you
wanted to reverse engineer something
properly you wouldn't try to steal the
source code to get the source code from
somewhere
you look at the actual thing right so
people have done by shots of it so this
is a very early one and everything
people could understand about it was
well there's some decoder some logic and
registers
that's everything that was understood
about the dive shop in 2001
some guy with the first name of polish
from Hungary take really high or a nicer
high-resolution photographs of the 6502
with some old Russian microscope
all black and white but really great and
she did a lot of work
reconstructing every single transistor
and drawing this schematic diagram which
is completed his every single transistor
yeah
and he did that all by himself went
alone and hungry and
then wrote a paper about it all in
Hungarian
yeah
so some people just he was translated
some some people translated some parts
of what he wrote and try to understand
because because I understood a lot about
what was going on and the 6502 because
of what he had learned from from copying
all those gates and but there were some
other guys
Greg Barry Brian and dead who just
recently so last it would they started
about one and a half years years ago to
do the whole thing again and properly
and very high quality and debugging
everything and making sure everything is
completely correct
and these are the guys from the visual
6502 project which you have probably
seen so i'll tell you a little so
originally it was supposed to be here
and to part of the slides so i'll just
show you what I understand about them
what he does this would be far too
dangerous for me is as cool as they
squirt hot sulfuric acid onto the chips
to get the plastic off and to get to the
actual chip
sometimes it doesn't look that pretty
but they work they can work if you clean
them properly and if you do it nicely
they can look like this let me show you
some clothes up here
so in in this stage to you should
actually still be working and so just
with a standard digital camera you can
get a resolution like this and we have
three parts here already
and by the way what's important is the
decoder is always on top that's the
correct orientation of 65 / -
so if you look closely was headed
sideways
so the next step you need really
high-resolution photographs of that and
you need some serious hardware for that
really good microscopes
what greg did was take lots and lots of
tiny photographs and then stitch them
together so one of these photographs
would be this one looks already nice but
just taking photographs of just the
surface wasn't enough because that
doesn't necessarily always show all the
layers because you can see all these
layers three four five six seven there
are many layers and you cannot always
distinguish those layers perfectly by
just looking at it from the top so as a
second step we also removed all the
layers with some extra chemicals to get
a shot like this so this destroys this
if you
but yeah it's for the greater good of
being able to reconstruct it better
so after stitching putting everything
together at the end hitter two hundred
or so megapixel picture and it turned
out six thousand by six thousand would
have been enough for reconstructing
everything and he wrote some tool to
basically draw the polygons the original
polygons of the traces and on top of the
the pictures that he took and so this is
the first picture
this is the second picture and so it
with his tool he threw the buyers and
through the traces and at the end you
get all the traces just on top of that
and that this would be the complete 6502
completely in in vectors and redrawn of
course need some debugging
so with with these tools and with a lot
of manpower you get from this photograph
to this completely digital and really
nicely colored presentation so if you
if if you look at the intersections of
all these traces and at what layers at
what levels they are and understand in
mass and how these processing this
processing was done from that you can
derive the necklace and the necklace is
basically all the transistors and how
the transistors are connected and how
the nodes are connected to the
transistors and this necklace alone
specifies the complete working of the
cpu so converting the netlist so this is
part 1 of the netlist this is part two
and these are the pull-up transistors
so all this is about seven kilobytes of
entropy is everything that is needed to
describe the 65 agree
so instead of trying to understand that
now from some diagrams or something
the best thing is to simulate it and
look at what's going on the question is
how would you stimulate to simulate all
that you basically you simulate all of
physics
so you if if you have on the outside you
have you can change pins for example you
toggle the clocks which then you have to
look at all
all the nodes that are going from there
to other transistors and you have to
look at what what the potential of of
these noses and they have to share all
the same potential and from there so you
can look at all of them
you look at the group value of the
potential of the group and you said all
the new notes to the new potential and
then you look at all the transistors
that are connected to all these notes
and you need to switch some of those
transistors and then you look at all the
notes behind those transistors and
repeat all that and if you repeat that
long enough
the system will stabilize and all the
notes will have some fixed potential and
then you're in the next stage and then
you can flip clock again and then you're
in the next cycle
this is of course very slow but it has
some really nice properties
so normally if you write an emulator I
mean first mm you later would be you
right it's not the original code
it's just a copy it's just a real
implementation the thing here is you
don't really
if you if you need to get it more and
more complete you need to add a little
more of data but a lot more of code gets
a lot more complexity in
complex and code if you do this with
this necklace approach the emulator
which emulates physics is always the
same
it's just a couple of hundred lines of
code and you just add more polygons you
just add more data
so with an emulator like that you can
emulate the photo or any other cpu done
in the same processor it doesn't even
have to be a cpu so I told you it was
pretty slow
what do you do if you want to get
something even slower you write in
JavaScript
yeah
so here's the whole html5 goodness of
the visual 64 to simulator that those
guys did I wasn't involved in that you
can see that it's all the blinking is
the clock counting up and all the
different races and changing the
potential you can see on the right
how the clock is counting up and you can
see it's about 23 hurts
and this is the maximum speed you can
get so it's about a million times slower
than a real chip but you can zoom in you
can look at all these things and there's
even an advanced mode in advanced mode
I've turned off the image now if you're
running you can look at a lot of the
internals a lot of the internal lines
what's going on there which component is
outputting what so this helps so much
and understanding what's going on in
these interesting edge cases but
speaking about simulation speaking about
being slow
of course if you rewrite it in see maybe
we can get a little faster
so this is where I come in and I wrote
as see version of this thing looks a
little like that
and if you run it so in this small demo
you'll see
I run the CD version and I feed it with
the microsoft basic from the c64 takes a
while
takes a while now it's kat accounting
the memory and the memory how many bytes
it has this many
ok yep
so seven seconds normally it's a couple
of milliseconds so it's still a thousand
times slower
we're getting there we're still thinking
about how how else we could make it
faster
so all these tools are really nice and
understanding stuff for example we can
automate something like i'm testing
through all the opcodes what do they do
which which registers do they change
which which inputs which outputs how
long do they take we can measure all
this completely automatically without
using real hardware because we have
completely perfectly simulated hardware
we can also do some interesting texts
like break transistors and see whether
the code still works and you can break a
lot of transistors
so this means that our code just doesn't
do everything that just doesn't exercise
all the transistors or another thing you
could do with it is
I mean sure you can use it in an
emulator but that's too slow what you
can do though is if you look at how many
emulators there exists for example this
is the list just a collection of nes
emulators out there and really if
everyone has written and 65 / - core for
these and there were only four people
here we have written 6502 course and
these always have bugs they're always
weird edge cases cited cases that that
aren't handled properly and with this
perfect emulator now you can run them
side by side and you can use the one to
test the other which is really nice
so what have we learned from all this
what can we now understand about what's
going on inside the CPU part 3 from the
inside out for everything here we have
to start with this really nice schematic
diagram again
let's look at it a little more detail
now program counter that's not all that
interesting sequenced and decoded this
is where the actual personality of the
6502 comes from the rest is pretty
standard the arithmetic and logic is
done like in any other cpu you have the
registers here and stack pointer and the
status register again and the two buses
so the s bus on the left is connected
more to a and the ALU and the s passes
more connected to the indexing part of
the system
let's start it where instruction
decoding starts or first let's start
with the with the timing generator
if you look at race what's going on if
you run code you can see there's a lot
of interleaving going on there
one instruction is still not finished
but the next one is pitched already this
is very much in contrast to something
like the z80 where everything is
divisible by four cycles it always has
its four cycles and then ok next
instruction for cycle 1 2 3 4
here we have a lot of interleaving so
it's very memory bounds very fast
priciples so in this example way or you
can see here the jump to the upper teens
not even finished
but we are in t0 in the first stage of
the of the next instruction fetch
already here we end in the decode of the
annex instruction here we execute the I
next instruction but we've already
finished ady instruction which is the
next one
so there is quite some interleaving
going on there
not in this case that if you look from
here because the ink instruction has to
write back out into memory in its last
cycle so we cannot fetch the next one at
the same time already
so because memory is already used so if
you don't have overlapping here
this is done really really efficiently
so timing generator
next piece is the decoder on that
decoder on is you can easily see that
thing on this it's the the other piece
the rom this is the big decoder it is 21
inputs it's really just a wrong as 21
interest in a hundred and thirty outputs
and the way it works is the inputs are
the instruction register which is the
code for example a 94 le a and T which
is the the cycle in which we are inside
the instruction and depending on the
opcode and the cycle
some of these lines will fire and it's
not always just one line it can be any
number of lines
so for example in this these four lines
were fire
so the the color on this is the complete
the code on let's look at the first ones
in a little more close up that the color
on compares the opcode and T as i said
so but it only looks at the the upper
six bits of the opcode the close to bits
just ignores because what it actually
looks at is this G value
I'll tell you about what Jesus on the
next slide for now just assume it's part
of the opcode and at that time so
there's always excess meaning don't care
so the first one would match to anything
that starts with 100 and then has a one
of the other bit and would imagine any
of the clock cycles of an any
instruction that that has this mask
so this G calculation this is this is a
rule for g how she works g1 g2 g3 are
three separate lines which going to the
decode rum and so this is a truth table
for it or a more useful to be this table
so there's a 00 01 10 and 11 corresponds
to g values of T 3 g1 g2 and the 11 case
that's undefined that's not used for the
6502 or what
how you can interpret this is that G
actually encouraged which register we're
working on so the lowest two bits is is
it a is x and y for certain instructions
others don't care about registers so
they don't care about the g so it's a
don't care it's an X there and you can
see this in your code table
the the columns 048 c and f 04 agency
are the ones that mostly deal with why
other ones that deal with why are
typically in those and then the next
column is all about a and the other one
it's all about X so it's all about the
lowest to bits
yep and here's a short video of the
decode Roman action you can see that all
the pink lines these are the lines that
are firing in other cycles
let's work real quick through an Lda an
LD X with the decoder on outputs
eliane elias are encoded very similarly
so they are the only difference is the G
value that they have
so in clock cycles 123 they do exactly
the same to have the same pla as a
decoder on PA rum outputs but in cycle
number for this is where the difference
is the one output something about a the
other one to something about X so this
is where they are different so moving on
from the code rom to random control
logic so they could decode them only
does that the front end for decoding and
ran around on controllogix the back end
for the coding it takes as an input the
130 bits from the first stage and what
it outputs is as you can see in this
close up early
yep these are all control lines which go
directly into some of the components
like the ALU or the buses
so this is very very specific and
controlling exactly what's going on
now let's look at this one example of
connecting SP 2 X and connecting x2 s.b
this is the S bus in X is connected to
it and you can either say let's load
from the S Plus into X or you can say
put the value of x 1 2 80's bus and
these two control lines control whether
this is the case
so this random control logic I don't
know where the name comes from maybe
because it's really that random it looks
random we haven't found anything that
makes it easier to understand what it's
doing
but let's let's look at the output of it
for example
so here's the output of an increment X
with the appeal a rom and the random
control logic in the first cycle in the
second cycle
now let's look at this on the schematic
diagram in the first cycle and increment
X has to get the information out of the
Exorcist onto the S Plus and it puts it
into the a input of the ALU but it also
has to put into the ALU is a one on the
other side to add it
this it does it by putting a 0 in there
by asserting this line and adding a
carrier of one and saying
yep we want to some so in the next cycle
we will have the result in em in the
aderhold register on the right of the lu
then in the second cycle
we have to get the whole register output
put it onto the S Plus with these these
two control lines and we store it into X
in there
there are a few more focus junk control
lines there to keep the ALU occupied
which are a side effect of how the way
is encoded and that everything is
encoded and the way they don't care
works so it doesn't have any influence
on what's actually going on but there
are two more lines that are asserted the
one that sits 0 flag and the other one
persistent in that sense the negative
flag from the output so break I acute MI
and reset
that's an interesting one how how this
is all sequence how this is done in the
sequencer in india and the logic
so as it is see again this is these
these are the vectors on the top of the
address space
it's all really similar what's going on
here and I a queue pushes the program
counter pushes the status register and
jumps over certain vector if you have a
break instruction software interrupt it
does the same thing but it puts the
break it onto the stack
NM is the same as an IQ but a different
vector and reset only jumps over vector
but that's not actually true because i
reset also does this exactly this
incredible pushes pc pushes p but nobody
cares because you have reset anyway so
this is not really known or useful or
interesting
so if you look at the whole table of
what's going on this no in push pc and
pee in the recent line here is actually
also yes so this is all rather
orthogonal is always the same code that
is running and so this is the code again
so it's there's two fetchers there's a
store of the PCH store pcl sort of p
fetching of the vector low fetching of
the vector higher than the future of the
new instruction
now the question is how can you how can
this be done for an interrupt for a
break instruction that's easy because
it's an instruction it gets sequence by
the PLA rom but how do you do that about
an intro and the trick here is done in
this box called a pretty cold logic you
can see that this has the interrupt and
reset pins as inputs
what it does is normally the instruction
register the opcode is fed by the code
that comes from the data bus but there's
also a zero input and there's the the IQ
and my and reset lines go in there
so whenever there's an IQ mi or a reset
then the instruction register is not
loaded with the actual instruction but
with a zero so what this does is it
injects 0 into the print to the program
stream and the 0 you might remember is
the brake instruction so this is really
neat trick here
injecting a break instruction which does
the whole sequence of what's going on
but afterwards it has to clean up and do
the right Victor and has to put the
brake flag properly and everything so it
has to cash that in information
somewhere but the sequences in has done
with the break but this is exactly where
this but came from you remember that the
break bug
if a break if you have a break and an IQ
happens at exactly the same time the
break we'll get ignored this is exactly
because of this because it injects a
break for the irq and then well it drops
the break
some other things that can be explained
with extra knowledge that we gain from
that is the RM w double store which is
actually already documented and so the
original documentation say say there's a
destroy destroy memory cycle in there
because they have it was just a don't
care if you if we look at the PLA from
outputs we can see that there's an
explicit
i mean it's it's it's done that way I
guess they optimize something so we
don't understand why but we can see
where it's happening
so this is illegal of course these are
the holy grail of all understanding the
6502 and I think we have made some
progress there
what people have done so far is mostly
well measure them and see what what are
they doing
and there were some theories about yeah
they seem to combine the ones that are
close to them but now we can say a lot
more about them
so the killer for example they're all
these most of them that end into they
just hold the machine
reset still works but you are accusing
NM eyes won't get delivered
what is happening here we can see in the
diagram by looking at the timing
generator because the timing generator
actually has an input from random
control logic because at some point I'm
the timing generator must know when to
the next pitch went to go to t0 again
and rent control logic knows that
because it has all the information about
from the decoder am indirectly what
state we are in what instruction we were
in and will tell it at some point
let's restart it 0 and this is exactly
what's going wrong with kill you have to
stay here on the left and the state more
detail with 0 1 2 3 4 as 45 as bits in
the killer code so that we are in t1 so
the one bit is set T to some random
stuff happens we don't care what's
happening there but what you can see is
that the way the sequence of works that
shifts the one to the right so it
shifted into t3 t4 t5 and nobody ever
says okay do the next fetch
so just shifted out and so we're now in
no state and nothing will have a match
again and we'll never catch the next
instruction so the next one will be just
the same and the machine is just wedged
so some are a little more helpful then
kill so if we make them lighter and
darker
depending on how useful they are there's
not there's a lot of knots which can be
rather easily explained by well there's
not there are no pla lines that match
them so they don't do much but the
timing is controlled by the one on the
left or the one on the right
because there's a don't care somewhere
but some interesting ones that can be
explained
especially because they are actually
useful is the essay acts and the lax
ones
so you can see whenever there's an L and
my ax
on the right you can see one that seems
to combine a index for storing and for
loading and this is because well I to do
before this is undefined here is not
actually undefined because of the way
that you wanted the g2 is calculated in
this 11 case this is actually the case
of g1 and g2 at the same time so the a
case is correct index case is correct
so if we go through step by step for an
Lda ldx and LAX
you will see that in the first
instructions while the LDA and the lax
do the same anyway into 123 124 the LDA
do something with a the other one does
something with X in LAX just true for
both
so this is the store into the register
so it stores it into a or in stores into
X at the same time because both of these
control lines are set so there's a lot
more about legal codes that can be
explained that way by just looking at
these traces but that would require
quite a lot of time and there are even
some that we're still looking at so the
question is what
there's a lot of people involved right
now that are doing this reverse
engineering on the mailing list and our
internal wiki
so what what is happening there is that
we're still investigating a lot more of
these things understanding how some of
them are unstable and how some other
things work so one thing that we have
some really interesting in
internal representation is this is the
mapping from from the up code
- what comes out of the random control
logic is the very last step so you can
rather easily look up
what's going on the bus in every cycle
of certain instructions but we're not
only investigating the 6502 by itself
but also the different the different 65
our tools that are out there are so many
things to do
for example does anyone recognize this
ship it is a tiny little while
not so tiny 65 or two on the bottom
right you can see here looks exactly
like a normal 65 / - this is the cpu in
the nes so it has the normal i guess
licensed version of 65 or two in there
and some video and audio logic in the
same chip and there's some other
versions of the 64 to as well looking at
them and comparing them is is can tell
us a lot about whether they fixed bugs
or something so for example and very old
versions and had some bug still was
fixed in standard 65 over to rockwell
licensed it
we looked at it looks a little different
there's a shrink used in later ,
computers and there's in the customers
to 64 and the c128 there's another drink
and 85 X series
so looking at all these would be
interesting but why stop there why not
look at other cpus we have really nice
representation of the ad and people are
looking at into vectorizing it right now
sixty thousand that thing is complex
that's 10 times as big as anything else
but yeah people are vectorizing that one
as well
why not use a quickly computer why not
you look well we have the 6502 already
let's do the video controller the audio
control of the i/o controllers and then
we could have a completely 64 in perfect
simulation and test all the other
emulators against it
this thing can all be done by
distributing the work because that would
be way too much for one single person
and it is actually working on making his
editor to work with more people
another thing to be done is just the
chips is not necessary enough
also x-raying the PCB is then you then
you have the full chip then here then
you have two full system that's
something that we're looking into or why
simulated in my simulated and software
if you can simulate it on fpga so
someone is also working on baking a 65
or two on two real hardware again and so
that was it if you want more information
on visual 6502 dorg
we have all the chip images all the
information we have a wiki we have the
JavaScript simulator that you know the
factorization - we'll be there shortly
64 to hackers is a mailing list with
lots of great people and it's closed
right now you can apply for membership
and we're planning to open it and of
course there is my blog
thank you
yeah
Thank You Michelle does anyone here has
questions